Today's דף daf is ע"ד, Ayin Dalet, well ע"ה, Ayin Hey, we
start on ע"ד עמוד ב Ayin Dalet amud bet and pick up
from the two dots והלש והאופה. ve-halash ve-ha'ofeh. So really at the
top of ע"ד עמוד ב Ayin Dalet amud bet we'll see if
we can make up for a little bit being behind. So five
lines from the bottom. Kneading and baking. אמר פפא Amar Pappa שביק
תנא דידן בישול סממנים דהוה במשכן ונקט אופה. shavik Tanna didan bishul
simmanim de-hava be-Mishkan ve-nakat ofeh. The question you know even when we
have a long, our תנא Tanna ignored the cooking of the sort
of, I don't know how to define סממנים, simmanim, but it's whatever
the various, yeah not spices though, but it's things from which you
extract dyes, you know which they're cooking various plants to extract dyes,
and it talks about baking herbs whatever, talk about baking which was
in the משכן Mishkan which was not in the משכן Mishkan and
the other one was in the משכן. Mishkan. תנא דידן סידורא דפת
נקט. Tanna didan siddura de-pas nakat. Our תנא Tanna is organizing it
based on the way of making bread. And as we said is
that just an organizational principle which is what it's normally assumed or
is it actually a different way of conceptually understanding the מלאכות melakhot
which is the way the יראים Yereim understands that. אמר רב אמר
רב אחא בר רב אוירא Amar Rav Amar Rav Aha bar Rav
Avira האי מאן דשדא סיכסא לאתונא, hai man de-shada sikhsa le-atuna, somebody
who throws a peg like a moist peg into an
oven, חייב משום מבשל hayyav mishum mevashel is חייב hayyav for cooking.
So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, obvious. You ask me as
soon as we're not talking about food nothing is פשיטא pshita that
that's cooking but okay. No, מהו דתימא mah de-teima I might have
thought לשרויי מנא קא מכוין lishuruyei maneh ka mekhavein maybe he's trying
to harden the peg which you do by I guess putting it
in there and evaporating the water, קא משמע לן דמרפא רפי kamoshma
lan de-mirpa rafi no first what happens is is that it gets
softer והדר קמיט ve-hadar kamit and then it gets hard. Now I
don't exactly know the science but what's more important is that the
גמרא Gemara takes it for granted that cooking applies to non-foodstuff and
it seems that the key definition it focuses on is the use
of heat in making something soft. Now for food it's important that
the use of heat does something to make it to change its
taste. There's even a whole debate, let's say it was edible before,
let's say you cooked an apple, is that cooking? Is it making
it only from something inedible to edible? Let's say you change its
taste but it tastes worse, is it only making it taste better?
But certainly by food some of that is debated but certainly by
food the idea of using heat to alter the taste is critical.
When it's non-food we tend to focus on the idea of the
use of heat in making it soft because that's what happens in
the normal process of cooking, although normally cooking with water as opposed
to other things baking and frying and so on. But that becomes
now a new definition of cooking applied to non-foodstuff. אמר רבה בר
רב הונא Amar Rava bar Rav Huna האי מאן דארתח כופרא hai
man de-arta kufra
if somebody put pitch in an oven and you heat it up,
not necessarily in an oven you heat it up, חייב משום מבשל
hayyav mishum mevashel that's also cooking because you basically liquefy the pitch.
פשיטא pshita that's obvious. מהו דתימא mah de-teima I might have thought
כיון דהדר ואיקשי keivan de-hadar ve-ikushi since after it gets liquefied you
leave it alone it will re-harden, אימא לא eima lo maybe that's
not, קא משמע לן kamoshma lan that it is. Now you know
is that because it's not defined since as cooking because it's not
softening it in a permanent way? Is it a problem is the
הוה אמינא hava amina about an issue about אינו מתקיים eino mitkayem
something that doesn't last, you know hard to know. I mean if
you heat up water you've cooked even though it'll cool down by
itself, maybe that's the answer, that it will last long enough to
do its function and here if you want liquefied pitch and tar
to pour on a street or whatever you're doing with it it
doesn't matter that it'll harden later you have now made a meaningful
transformation. But again it does not matter according to the גמרא Gemara
that's not food. I should also mention what also doesn't matter is
that it's even not something that grows from the ground. Now cooking
is not limited to גידולי קרקע, gidulei karka, some of these other
things were, but you know you can cook meat obviously and be
חייב. hayyav.
But anyway here it is interesting as well that we are not
limiting it to the objects. Pitch is even included. Where do you
get pitch from? Some type of a like petroleum based thing? Yeah
okay fine. All right so now the גמרא Gemara says okay we
get to that. אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא Rava האי מאן
דעביד חביתא hai man de-avid khavita now that's the end of the
whole issue of cooking and we're not even going to really discuss
kneading. We're just quickly zooming through these chip-chip-chip. Now of course we
had three פרקים prakim more or less devoted to cooking, I mean
a lot of them were the דרבננ'ס derabbanans of cooking, but so
it's understandable we don't have to say that much more about cooking
maybe only apply it to the non-foodstuff. But a lot of these
other things I mean לש lash tell me what לש lash is.
So a lot of this as I have told you is going
to come up in later פרקים prakim in a certain way you
can see the rest of שבת Shabbat not all of it because
of course we're gonna have to you know do הוצאה hotsaa again
and have מוקצה muktsa again but I mean הוצאה hotsaa is one
of the מלאכות melakhot but we have a lot of it. But
a lot of the rest of the מסכת masekhet is very various
ways of elaborating on these
ל"ט מלאכות lamed tet melakhot sometimes the דאורייתא de-oraita category sometimes the
דרבנן. derabbanan. Sadly it's not organized that way. It's not like wouldn't
it be very nice if the next פרק perek started us off
with חורש horaysh and then went on to זורה zoreh right? So
it's more like what the רמב"ם Rambam does, but the organization won't
exactly be there but it's not all being elaborated on here. So
now what we move into is these
little like almost puzzles or like you know about the ל"ט מלאכות
lamed tet melakhot not exactly let's see. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: האי
מאן דעביד חביתא, Hai man de'avid chavitah, if somebody makes a pottery
barrel, חייב משום שבע חטאות. chayav mishum sheva chatatot. You get seven
sin offerings, because you'll do seven different מלאכות. melachos. תנורא, Tanura, if
you make an oven, which is pottery but it's glazed over afterwards,
חייב משום שמונה חטאות, chayav mishum shemoneh chatatot, eight. So now the
גמרא's Gemara not going to tell you what they are. You have
to look at רש"י. Rashi. Okay, so go figure that out, that's
a little puzzle, it's a little homework assignment for the reader. Go
figure out how many חטאות chatatot you can make by making a
barrel. So let's just tell you quickly what רש"י Rashi says. Okay,
grinding up the earth is טוחן, tochen, because רש"י Rashi שבע חטאות,
sheva chatatot, I'm not going to read it all inside but it's
about seven lines before the line gets wide. So you have grinding,
okay. We had already grinding on non-food, you know, we had grinding
on wood and so on. So grinding up the wood, the clay
that you're going to use. I must say that is interesting, I
don't know the process, but again similar to the idea of of
mincing, you know, the normal טוחן tochen in the by the by
wheat is you pulverize something and you make it into powder. When
you grind up earth to make use it for pottery, you just
make it separate it into like normal, you know, do you actually
change it or do you just break it up into little pieces?
But anyway, if רש"י Rashi says you can mince beets and be
חייב chayav for טוחן, tochen, so okay, you're grinding up dirt.
Then you select out the the the what do you call it
the stones, okay, that's בורר. borer. Then that's two, then you sift
it, okay, with a sieve, that's three. Then you sift the earth?
Yeah, because you want clean dirt to use for your plaster or
whatever your pottery or plaster. Okay, then you then you mix this
dirt with water whatever to make it into a clay. So into
a moldable thing, that's לש, losh, adding water to like little, you
know, to separate pieces to make it into one homogeneous mass. That's
essentially what לש losh is like adding water to the flour. Then
you you smooth over the plaster, that's ממרח, memareiach, smoothing, which we
haven't gotten to yet, which they did by the leather.
One minute. And then you make the fire, that's מבעיר, mavir, and
then you put it in the fire and that's מבשל. mevashel. Okay,
of course, does it get soft first? Until now the גמרא Gemara
was saying that מבשל mevashel needed to get soft, it would seem
there it only gets hard. Anyway, that's how רש"י Rashi says that
you and רש"י Rashi says don't count digging the hole for the
dirt because that's what we said before, that's like מלאכה שאינה צריכה
לגופה melachah she'einah tzerichah legufah if you dug the hole for the
dirt. Others have different lists. Why do you get eight for the
תנור? tannur? So רש"י Rashi says because after you're done with it
in the oven then you put on it some type of a
plaster. Now so what? According to רש"י Rashi we already had ממרח,
memareiach, smoothing something on. So רש"י Rashi says that's מכה בפטיש, makeh
b'patish, doing the last act. When it happens automatically by being in
the oven and you're not doing anything, it's just passively being finished,
that's not מכה בפטיש, makeh b'patish, but when you actively do some
final act like you would do here to put some plaster on
an oven, that would be מכה בפטיש. makeh b'patish. There's an interesting
debate of רש"י Rashi against תוספות Tosafot and the גאונים Geonim whether
to count one of the things here as בונה. boneh. Can you
be בונה boneh a כלי? kli? רש"י Rashi says no, אין בנין
בכלים. ein binyan bekeilim. תוספות Tosafot says no, אין בנין בכלים ein
binyan bekeilim is not an absolute principle. It means that a lot
of times if you're reassembling something, there's not בנין, binyan, but if
you really create a vessel from scratch, that is בונה boneh and
it applies even to vessels. So that's an issue that we will
see later. Okay, that's your seven and your eight. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara continues, אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: האי מאן דעביד חלסא, Hai
man de'avid chalsa, if you make like a type of a reed
wicker basket. Does it sound like vinegar? What? No, that's חלא. chala.
חייב אחת עשרה חטאות. chayav achas esreh chatatot. You get eleven. וחייטי
לפורמיה, Vechaiti lefumieh, and if you basically make a lip at the
on on its opening,
חייב תליסר, chayav telisar, you get thirteen. So what are the eleven?
I'll just say quickly what רש"י Rashi says. First of all you
are cutting the, you know, you're pruning a tree to get the
sticks, and רש"י Rashi says, now this is a little of course,
you know, trick, oh, so since you're also trying to prune the
tree, so therefore he gets two, pruning and and cutting which is
a type of planting and
תולש, toleish, you're uprooting something from where it's growing, okay, קוצר. kotzer.
Okay, then you after they all fall on the ground, you gather
them together in a pile, that's מעמר. me'ameir. Then you select out
the good ones, that's בורר. borer. Okay, then you smooth them out,
the sticks to be used, that's ממחק, memachek, smoothing.
What how many are we up to? Five. Hold on.
You got to make sizes and sizes.
Right. Then you basically רש"י Rashi says then you break them into
two or three, רש"י Rashi says that's טוחן. tochen. Now that's very
strange because טוחן tochen you would think is tiny little pieces, so
I don't get that exactly. Then he says if you cut them
to particular sizes, that's מחתך, mechatech, that's seven.
Now then whatever, you have to weave them. So putting them on
the loom is מיסך. meisach. Then weaving them is אורג. oreig. That's
nine. Wait
a minute,
oh, then you also made the actual structure of the loom, the
whatever we'll talk about it, but there's three things associated with weaving,
you did all three. So that is ten.
And then, and then after it's all done, you trim the edges,
and that's מכה בפטיש, Makeh B'Patish, that's eleven. Okay, how do you
get thirteen by making the lip? So because you basically do some
knot, some sewing and knotting, and that's תופר Tofer and קושר. Kosher.
So that's thirteen, okay? So it's like a little fun thing about
how can you get how many different categories of מלאכה Melacha can
you get in one process? All right, but anyway the interesting חידוש
Chidush in רש"י Rashi I would say is טוחן Tochen by by
the things, I'm not sure what people do with it, but as
we said טוחן Tochen already is a little bit challenging.
I don't think, I mean, you know, I don't think that that
that that comment is too much expanded on in terms of the
parameters of טוחן. Tochen. Yes.
Actually I was going to ask about that, these these different opinions
of ראשונים Rishonim on what these are might have הלכה. Halacha.
Right. That is absolutely true. And that is discussed, particularly the question
about parameters of מכה בפטיש, Makeh B'Patish, parameters of בונה. Boneh. This
רש"י Rashi that said טוחן Tochen in here which does not seem
to fit is best you know to best of my I can
I can research it but I don't think it plays a major
a major role in the parameters of טוחן. Tochen.
מכה בפטיש Makeh B'Patish the thing is you said before is not
something that happens on its own, because otherwise if you cook it
you'd always be
מכה בפטיש.
Makeh
B'Patish.
Exactly. Right, exactly. There's a general question if you have מכה בפטיש
Makeh B'Patish באוכלין, B'Ochlin, but that's true. All right, now, end of
the narrow lines. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, הטווה צמר שעל גבי בהמה
בשבת. HaToveh tzemar she'al gabei behemah b'Shabbos. You basically took your sheep
indoors and you did this trick in which you spun wool off
of directly off of the sheep, okay? So חייב שלש חטאות, Chayav
shalosh chata'os, you get three sin offerings, אחת משום גוזז, Achas mishum
gozez, one for shearing, ואחת משום מנפץ V'achas mishum menapeitz for for
combing, presumably in the twisting of it you're doing something to get
the gunk out, I don't know how, maybe you're using your hands
in the process of pulling it, ואחת משום טווה, V'achas mishum toveh,
and one for spinning. ורב כהנא אמר אין דרך גזיזה בכך. V'Rav
Kahana amar ein derech gezizah b'kach.
What's the difference if you shear the sheep first or not?
Right, that's the point, even if it's being done as one process,
you're doing three things.
But how are there three things within it though? What? You're saying
there's three things in it? Yeah, there's weaving, this is spinning, oh
this
is after the threads, so it's three things about setting up the
loom and doing the weaving itself. This is creating the thread.
And even though it's all being done in one action. So רב
כהנא Rav Kahana says back and this was similar to a discussion
we had a day or two ago, אין דרך גזיזה בכך ואין
דרך מנפץ בכך. Ein derech gezizah b'kach v'ein derech menapeitz b'kach. So
that's all very cute, but that is not the normal way of
shearing and it is not the normal way of combing, ואין דרך
טוויה בכך, v'ein derech tveiyah b'kach, and it's not the normal way
of spinning. So again, right, you're not חייב Chayav anything. So the
question always is how unusual, as I said, what is the parameters
of שינוי, Shinui, but he says that you know he says this
does not qualify. הגמרא HaGemara says ולא? V'lo? Does it not? והתניא
משמיה דרבי נחמיה, Vehatanya mishmei d'Rabbi Nechemia, we taught in the name
of רבי נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemia, שטוף בעזים וטוו בעזים, Shatuf b'izim v'tavu
b'izim, that you know when they said וכל אשה חכמת לב בידיה
טוו, V'chol ishah chachmas lev beyadeiha tavu, all wise women spun with
their hands, so he said what made them so wise? So he
said ah, they did a whole trick, they had the goats go
into the water you know go into the river whatever go into
the water and they cleaned it all off and then you know
and they spun it straight off of the goats. So you see
that's what they did so it was a normal way of doing
it. אלמא טוויה גבי בהמה שמה טוויה. Alma tveiyah gabei behemah shemah
tveiyah. You see it is called spinning. הגמרא HaGemara says no, חכמה
יתירה שאני. Chochma yesirah shani. That was because they had this whole
trick. So but for that, you know, so but for other people
that is not a normal way of doing things. Interesting question is
for them would they be חייב Chayav and maybe not, maybe it's
not defined as מלאכה. Melacha. What? I know. And in the משכן.
Mishkan. That is true, and Mike makes a correct point, that it
is interesting that that even though we're learning from the משכן, Mishkan,
we apply normal parameters of of you know דרך Derech onto that
and we'll see something similar to that in a little minute. If
you look at תוספות Tosafos חכמה יתירה, Chochma yesirah, ועושים אותם, v'osim
osam, and even if you did it that way, בטלה דעתו אצל
כל אדם, batlah da'ato eitzel kol adam, doesn't matter if you're able
to do this, this is not considered normal and so that's also
interesting, even though for you it is, yes. Ari, you had a
question? No, look down here. Okay, fine. So now the גמרא Gemara
says
okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, we taught, התולש את הכנף, HaTolesh es
hakanaf, you pick off a feather from a bird. Interesting question, does
it have to be a live bird or even a dead bird?
This is גזיזה, Gezizah, like shearing something off, but it's an interesting
question as I said would it include a dead animal?
And נוצה Notzah feather, and כנף kanaf would be a wing?
A wing. I'm sorry, yeah, but רש"י Rashi basically says it's like
the feathers of the wing. Of the, anyway, והקוטמו, V'hikmeto, and then
you snip it, והמרטו, V'himarto, and you then sort of remove the
feathers from the you know from the what's it called? Quill. Quill,
yeah, essentially, is that what it's called a quill before it's made
into a pen? Anyway, whatever, the stick part of the wing,
חייב שלש חטאות. Chayav shalosh chata'os. So you're חייב Chayav three sin
offerings. What are they? What are they? אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish
Lakish, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish explains, תולש חייב משום גוזז, Tolesh chayav
mishum gozez, plucking the feather is גוזז. Gozez. That's not a big
חידוש. Chidush. That's you know cutting something off of a living let's
assume although that's debated animal, a person, because you want the thing
itself. That's גוזז. Gozez. Today's, קוטם, Kotem, I should mention it's an
interesting question if I, let's say, clip my fingernails or give myself
a haircut or give somebody else a haircut, is that גוזז? gozez?
I'm doing, you know, cutting something off of a living thing, I'm
doing something constructive and, you know, positive, it's not destructive, but I'm
not trying to get the thing itself. I'm trying to improve the
thing I'm cutting it from. So that's an interesting question, but here
clearly it's גוזז. gozez. קוטם Kotem חייב משום מחתך, chayav mishum mechatech,
cutting your חייב chayav because of מחתך. mechatech. Now why are you
cutting if מחתך mechatech requires what are you cutting? If you're just
cutting off the bottom edge, the pointy part at the bottom, so
why מחתך mechatech has to be that you care about a very
specific size? So רש״י Rashi says you're not cutting off the pointy
part at the bottom. רש״י Rashi says you're cutting off the tip
of it and you can use the tip of the feather for,
you know, for instead like for down, but you want that tip,
the part that you can cut off and use effectively is only
a certain amount of the tip. Okay, the rest you're going to
have to strip off of the stick. So therefore you want that
to be a particular size, you cut it in a particular place,
and therefore that's מחתך. mechatech. רש״י Rashi also suggests that maybe because
in the end you're going to use it for a quill, so
you're being specific where you're cutting it now so you could use
the end product as a type of a quill. So that's מחתך.
mechatech. And ממרט, memaret, the stripping of the feathers, חייב משום ממרח
chayav mishum memachek is for smoothing. Now that's very interesting and important
because smoothing normally is what they did as part of the process
of making the leather. Here, normally you would think that smoothing requires
a desire for the thing that you're smoothing to be smooth and
it's improving the thing you're doing. Okay, here you're just all you
want to do is get the feathers off. You don't care that
it's smooth. And nevertheless, it's because of ממרח, memachek, although maybe not,
maybe if your desire is also to use it as a quill,
then you do want it smooth. Right, you understand the difference? Are
you interested in what's left? And that becomes a very important question
about exactly what are the parameters of smoothing, you know, the big
question we'll see in a minute about like putting some type of
a poultice on somebody and smearing some type of a salve, the
big question about brushing teeth, is that ממרח? memachek? Okay, so do
you really want like your toothpaste to be a smooth thing? You're
just trying to apply it in all places, you know, and how
much does part of ממרח memachek mean that you are in fact
smoothing or you're trying to actually create a smoothed object?
Could you be חייב chayav for two things
at the exact same time? Yes, the גמרא Gemara had it before.
Pruning, pruning if you also if you want the wood, is חייב
שתים.
chayav shtayim. So therefore if I'm shaving, then it'd be גוזז gozez
and ממרח memachek too, right?
Because I want the skin smooth. That's interesting, if that would be
considered ממרח memachek removing something, well that's here you're removing and you're
ממרח. memachek. That's an interesting point. So maybe there's an aspect of
ממרח. memachek. That's an interesting question. Okay, yeah, it's very similar to
this.
Yeah, isn't there also a question on שבת Shabbos whether you can
use certain creams and not others, right? Correct, right, right, right.
So I will just say that you make one quick comment about
that. The גמרא, Gemara, you know, as I tell people, I say
סיכה sicha is only אסור assur on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. סיכה
Sicha was the putting oil on the skin, right? It's not אסור
assur on שבת. Shabbos. So that's like a good a good, you
know, sort of rule of thumb. If something is the viscosity of
oil or less, it's not a problem because they put oil on
their skin on שבת. Shabbos. The question is if it's thicker than
that and you smooth it on your body on your skin, is
that considered a type of ממרח? memachek? And part of it has
to do we'll see something like that coming up. What, you know,
in that case what I tell people mostly to do is like
to dab it on and not to smooth, or like the Desitin
with the baby, I mean the creamy Desitin is better because it's
again smoother. But anyway, you know, to basically dab it on and
then you just put the or you put on the diaper just
dab it in different places on the bottom and then you put
on the diaper and the baby'll take care of smearing it all
over its own bottom. Yes.
That also comes up for liquid liquid soap.
A lot of us don't use liquid soap.
Yeah, although that's true, although liquid soap is very funny because of
that because
first of all to me I think liquid soap is no more
viscous than oil, number one. Number two is, as opposed to things
even like toothpaste, you don't want a thin layer of soap to
remain on your skin, so you want it to interact and then
come off and you're not trying to like apply it, you know,
flat to apply it in a with anyway, these are the questions
of ממרח. memachek. Let's go on. הקושר והמתיר, Hakoasher v'hamatir,
knotting and unknotting, we'll have a whole פרק perek about קשירה. kshira.
Anyway, קשירה במשכן היכא הוי? Kshira bamishkan heicha havae? So the גמרא
Gemara is asking more secondary questions than basic parameters which we'll get
later. Where did they knot in the משכן? Mishkan? אמר רבא שכן
קושרים ביתדות אהלים. Amar Rava shekein koshrim biyatedos ohalim. No,
when they would make their, you know, when they would have to
tie down the the what do you call it the the
right, the stake, the the yeah I know but the thing on
the top, anyway the tent part, they'd have to tie it down
to a peg, so therefore that would be knotting.
So presumably this doesn't mean their own personal tents,
this means actual משכן, Mishkan, רש״י Rashi says יסודות. yesodos. You'd say
יתדות המשכן, yitdot haMishkan, right? So the יריעות yeriyot of the משכן,
Mishkan, which were the, which were, you know, the curtains around the
חצר אהל מועד, Chatzer Ohel Moed, they would tie it down with
a peg on a peg. So, גמרא Gemara says: No, האי קושר
על מנת להתיר הוא, hai kosher amnat lehatir hu,
that's done for the sake of undoing because it's only going to
be temporary. Now that's a very strange because you want it there
for as long as you're going to stay there, right? And it's
obviously effective. Like we said before, you're making tar, you're liquefying it,
it's going to get hard, but you're making it a way that
you can use it now. It's very strange that גמרא Gemara considers
that קושר על מנת להתיר. kosher amnat lehatir. That says something about
a קשר, kesher, that a קשר kesher might maybe more than other
things. Maybe קושר על מנת להתיר kosher amnat lehatir is different than
just אינו מתקיים. eino mitkayem. You would not have called this אינו
מתקיים. eino mitkayem. It is מתקיים, mitkayem, you leave it alone, it'll
stay, you know, it's doing a function right now. But maybe קשר,
kesher, the idea is what a real sense of a permanent knot.
And therefore, this is it's harder to define something as a קשר,
kesher, it maybe not other things, this wouldn't be temporary, but a
knot maybe is supposed to be permanent.
So גמרא Gemara asks: Where is it undoing? Well,
right.
So we will see about this when we get to that פרק.
perek.
Because they never knew how long it would stay.
Well, גמרא Gemara says that elsewhere. גמרא Gemara says, is it בבלי
Bavli or the ירושלמי? Yerushalmi? It might be the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Anyway,
but it basically says since they were totally dependent on God, so
you know they were prepared to be there for the next fifty
years if the if the cloud didn't move, so that makes it
permanent.
Just that when they when they hit they
never knew, could be a day. Exactly. So that could make it
always defined as impermanent, but גמרא Gemara has a place where it
makes it defined as permanent. They're prepared to be there indefinitely. But
of course that would have been another good answer here. So גמרא
Gemara does use that by like אהל, ohel, but for some reason
here it's interested in finding another example of קושר. kosher.
Going to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. I understand. Okay, so גמרא Gemara
says
like this: אלא אמר אביי, Ella amar Abaye, שכן אורגי יריעות, sheken
orgei yeriyot, people that were weaving the the curtains, שנפסקה להם נימא,
shenifska lahem nima, if a string would break, קושרו, koshreno, you would
knot it, right? What if a string in the weave breaks, you
would knot it together. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, תירצת קושר,
tiratzta kosher, fine, now you've got an example of knotting, מתיר מאי
איכא למימר, matir mai ika lemeimar, what do you do of undoing?
And again, as part of making the משכן. Mishkan. וכי
תימא, Vechi teima, if you say
דמירמי ליה תרי חוטי קטרי בהדי הדדי, demiremi lei trei chuti kitrei
behadi hadadi, let's say you have two knots on two threads right
next to each other. Then it's real obvious, then it like sticks
out, right? One knot you can get away with. Two knots right
next to each other you can't get away with. So what are
you going to have to
do? So שרי חד וקטיר חד, shari chad vekatir chad, you'll have
to undo one and knot the other one and keep the other
one knotted. So you'll have to undo a knot if it if
it winds up alongside another one with a knot in it and
it looks bad. So גמרא Gemara says they wouldn't do that. השתא
לפני מלך בשר ודם אין עושים כן, Hashta lifnei melech basar vadam
ein osin kein, you wouldn't do it if you were making a
curtain for an earthly king, לפני מלך מלכי המלכים הקדוש ברוך הוא
עושים, lifnei melech malchei hamlachim hakadosh baruch hu osin, would you do
it in front of God? Because if you leave one of them
unknotted, you'll see a hole and that'll even be worse. So they
would never do that. So רש״י Rashi says so what would they
do? רש״י Rashi basically says they'd pull out the string and start
again. But anyway, so they would not anyway you would also ask
that that's you know that's not מתיר על מנת לקשור matir amnat
likshor and other aspects. Anyway, גמרא Gemara doesn't like that answer. So
גמרא Gemara says:
So what is it? אלא אמר רבא ואיתימא רב עילאי, Ella amar
Rava ve'iteima Rav Ilai, שכן צדי חלזון קושרים ומתירים. sheken tzedei chilazon
koshri'in umatirin. When they had to make the nets for trapping the
the snails for getting the תכלת, techelet, you know, the
the blue dye, they would to make a net you have to
knot and unknot and make a lot of knots and adjust the
net, and therefore that would be part of it. So it's many
stages removed but it was still part of the process of making
the משכן. Mishkan. Yes.
Two questions. One is that there's like you know sort of something
that you're trying to do לכתחילה, lechatchila, the other is oh this
is the בדיעבד, bedi'avad, in other words you don't want your knot
to happen. Okay, so that's a good
and we are saying there's a problem. And the other question is
just mechanically, didn't we say that the חילזון chilazon is by the
sea and these people are in the desert, so how did it
get in?
Oh, okay, that I don't know, but the anyway but the other
point is what they
went
around the sea,
yeah, maybe maybe before they left the ים סוף. Yam Suf. Anyway,
but but that is a good point that גמרא Gemara was willing
to consider something that was not a sort of a part you
know was part of the process of making it assuming that it
was there were going to be problems, not part of the process
assuming no problems. Maybe there's a good מוסר שמועס mussar shmuess in
that. Okay, about you know even the תורה Torah understands that it's
not going to be perfect and even that's part of the process.
Okay, והתופר שתי תפירות, vehatofer shtei tefirot, making but anyway in the
end גמרא Gemara didn't stay with that. Making two stitches, והלא קיימא,
vahalo kayma, what do you mean two stitches? If you make two
stitches it it'll just undo itself, so that's really an אינו מתקיים.
eino mitkayem. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbah
bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, והוא שקשרן, vehu sheksharan, no, it's
where you made a knot at the ends of the stitches and
then the stitch won't pull out. Now that might also be קושר,
kosher, maybe. Okay, maybe not. Maybe it depends if you make a
double knot, a professional knot, but that doesn't matter because you've you're
חייב chayav because
of
of of תופר. tofer. Why, why threading your shoe is not תופר?
tofer? Is your question?
You're tying at the end, that's the final.
What are you talking, making tying your shoe should be תופר tofer
because because this stuff is already pre-stitched. Well, first of all, a
type of thing that's done to be done and undone or whatever
is different, it's not really תופר, tofer, and threading your shoes is
not תופר. tofer. But the shoelace. But the other question that you're
asking, which is a good one, is if it's not מתקיים mitkayem
until after you make the second knot. You make the second knot
after you finish doing the act of תפירה. tefira. So you know,
so can it become a מלאכה melacha because of what you did
after the מלאכה? melacha? You know, until you made the second knot,
it was אינו מתקיים. aino mitkayem. Right? So that's also interesting. Maybe
one knot is enough. Maybe it was pre-knotted at the end, have
to be very complicated in order to do that. So it does
sound like if you're, you know, that if you have to do
something afterwards to make sure it's מתקיים, mitkayem, that could be enough
to have made the previous thing a מלאכה, melacha, which wasn't what
you were asking, that's what I wanted to say. Yes, Charlie?
A tying clothing stitches, such as ties or scarves?
Yeah, that's similar to that question. That's more about קושר, koshair, not
about תופר. tofer. Here we'll talk about it, we have a whole
פרק perek about קושר. koshair. Here we just have an example as
I said, that you have to have a knot at the end
in order to make it something that is lasting. הקורע על מנת
לתפור, Hakoreia al m'nas litfor, tearing for the sake
of sowing, because otherwise it would be considered destructive, and maybe specifically,
always a question by these things that have these qualifiers in them.
As we mentioned in the משנה mishna and תוספות tosafos mentions, you
know, a number of them just say the simple heading. לש, Lash,
אופה. ofeh. Others have tell you the minimum amount. Others tell you
it's only על מנת al m'nat to do something else. So why
did it say that by some and not others? Maybe it's just
a application of a general rule, that something has to be constructive
and not destructive, or maybe it's very specific. No,
קורע koreia has to be not just there, maybe there's other ways
קורע koreia could be constructive, but this specifically has to be a
הקורע על מנת לתפור. koreia al m'nas litfor. And that's part of
the definition of the מלאכה melacha of קורע. koreia. So let's take
a look. אקרעא במשכן מי הוה? A kria bamishkan mehava? When did
they tear things in the משכן? mishkan? So רבה בר רב זירא,
Rabba bar Rav Zeira, אמרי תרווייהו, amri tivaihu, רבה Rabba and רב
זירא, Rav Zeira, they both say, and here's again an example of
things not being perfect. שכן יריעה שנפל בה דרנא, Sheken yeriyah shenafal
bah darna, if you have a curtain that like a moth hole
fell into it. קורין בה, Korin bah, you tear away the area
around the moth hole, ותופרין אותה, vetofri nosa, and then you would
resew in its place. So you would tear something bad away and
replace it
with another patch.
And you do that? מלאכה מלאכה?
Melacha melacha? I was wondering the same thing. Okay, so anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב: Amar Rav
Zutra bar Tuvia, amar Rav: המותח חוט של תפירה בשבת. Hamoteiach chut
shel tefira beshabbos. Let's say you have something sewn on, but it's
loose, and what you do is you stretch the thread to tighten
it back up. This is obviously, this could happen very interestingly, well
I'll tell you where I see this happening by קושר, kosher, which
is people are playing with their ציצית tzitzis and they are tightening
the knots of their ציצית. tzitzis. Okay, but you could also have
it, let's say you've got your button that is a little bit
pulling off and you find the thread and you pull it tight,
so now it's tight against your garment. Okay, so that, he says,
you're חייב חטאת. chayav chatas. So you didn't actually do the threading,
but you did an act which basically tightened something with a stitch.
So even if you didn't actually do the threading, that's תופר. tofer.
Now I don't exactly, it would have to be a case where
it would be קיימא, kiyama, right? If the thing was, so what?
Now you still have a loose thread and two seconds later it's
going to loosen again. You might have an example where it's אינו
מתקיים. aino mitkayem. But if it does last for a significant period
of time, even without doing the stitches, that is a type of
תפירה. tefira. אבל לא. Aval lo. Now of course now we're going
to have two other completely irrelevant things, but these were all said,
רב זוטרא בר טוביה Rav Zutra bar Tuvia in the name of
רב. Rav. Irrelevant at least to, relevant to תורה, Torah, irrelevant to
our immediate discussion.
Tightened by stitches then, you're saying, if it... yeah,
well, stitches.
What? Yeah. So תפירה tefira as a, it is a question, right?
תפירה tefira is primarily about stitching two things together. There is a
question about other ways of combining things. So let's say I glued
two things together. Would that be a type of a תופר? tofer?
Would that be a type of a קושר? koshair? Okay, but presumably
תפירה tefira can include things other than stitches, but here we're saying
in a context of
stitches. Okay, we have not yet discussed other cases.
Now other statements in the same מאן דאמר man d'amar in the
name of רב. Rav.
והלומד דבר אחד מן המגוש, Vehalomeid davar echad min hamagush, somebody who
learns even one thing from a magi, some magician, חייב מיתה chayav
misa is deserving of death. והיודע, Vehayodeia, and the third thing is,
לחשב תקופות ומזלות ואינו חושב, lechasheiv tkufos umazalos ve'eino chosheiv, somebody who
knows how to figure
out the astronomy and the seasons and the stars and does not
actually do the computations, אסור לספר הימנו. assur lesaper imanu. You can't
talk to him. Okay, that person has really done something deeply
offensive. מגוש, Migushto, what is this מגוש? megushta? We have... רב ושמואל,
Rav uShmuel, Rav and Shmuel debate. חד אמר חרשי, chad amar charshi,
one say it is a like a witch, somebody does witchcraft, וחד
אמר גידופי, v'chad amar giddufi, which is לגדף ligadef means
like to a blasphemer, Rashi says also an idolator. Okay? דאסתייע
דרב דאמר גידופי, distayei d'Rav d'amar giddufi, let's conclude that Rav is
the one that says it's a blasphemer slash idolator. Why? דאמר רב
זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב, d'amar Rav Zutra bar Tuvia amar Rav,
because we have just said in his name, הלומד דבר אחד מן
המגוש חייב מיתה, halomed davar echad min hamagush chayav misa, that if
you learned something from him you're deserving of death. Would that be
true if he were a somebody who did witchcraft? Why not? דאי
סלקא דעתך חרשי, de'isalka da'itchach charshi, because if he were somebody who
did witchcraft,
הכתיב לא תלמד לעשות, hakasiv lo tilmad la'asos, you cannot learn to
do like these things, to do witchcraft, אבל לדרשה הוא, aval lidrosha
hu, but the drasha is אבל אתה לומד להבין ולהורות, aval ata
lomed lehavin ulehoros, you're allowed to learn not for the sake of
doing, but you're allowed to learn in order to understand. Now why
do you want to understand? Rashi says, well, because if somebody comes
and tries to say let's say they're a נביא navi and they
do miraculous-looking stuff, you'll be able to figure out if maybe they're
really just using witchcraft on you. Okay? So not just for abstract
intellectual knowledge, he has it like for a halakhic purpose. So the
point is, if this guy מגוש magush was a somebody who did
witchcraft, why did we say you're חייב מיתה? chayav misa? You're allowed
to learn from him. How else are you going to
learn? It says you're allowed to learn for the sake of understanding
if not for the sake of doing. Now what's fascinating is, if
we said if I wanted to learn witchcraft or any field, where
would I go? Where would I go? To a witch. No, I
would go, well I, normally I'd say I would go to the
books. Now I'd say well I'd go to Wikipedia or something. But
anyway, but what's interesting is they say if you're allowed to learn
that means you're absolutely actually allowed to go to the expert. Because
it was an oral culture. They didn't have books. So if you're
allowed to learn, you're allowed to go to the people who know.
So obviously Rav who says it's a problem cannot be saying that
this person is somebody who knows witchcraft. Someone says it's real too.
Well, that's also true, the implicit assumption is, you know, רמב"ם Rambam
would say you're learning it to know their tricks and you're learning
it to know why it's false, you know, so there's a rationalist
way of trying to translate this as well. But the point of
the גמרא Gemara is Rav says this harsh statement that you're חייב
מיתה, chayav misa, he wouldn't say it on an allowed thing we
know you're allowed to learn these
things if you don't want to do them, he wouldn't do it
to, you know, have some fun.
Yeah, but he didn't say that qualification. He said
it's blanket forbidden
to learn even one thing from him. Why would he say that?
It must be we're not talking about somebody who does witchcraft, we're
talking about a blasphemer-idolator and you can't be learning from him because
he will lead you astray. Okay, so that's the first statement, or
the second. Now we get to the issue
of תקופות ומזלות. tkufos umazalos.
דאסתייע, distayei, so that was a good proof. אמר רבי שמעון בן
פזי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי משום בר קפרא, Amar Rebbe Shimon
ben Pazi amar Rebbe Yehoshua ben Levi mishum Bar Kappara, כל היודע
לחשב תקופות ומזלות ואינו חושב, kol hayodea lachashev tkufos umazalos ve'eino choshev,
anybody that knows how to compute the various, you know, seasons and
the constellations
and does not do it, עליו הכתוב אומר, alav hakasiv omer, regarding
him the verse says,
ואת פעל ה' לא יביטו ומעשה ידיו לא ראו. ve'es po'al Hashem
lo yabitu uma'aseh yadav lo ra'u. The actions of God they did
not
contemplate and God's handiwork they did not see. You have an opportunity
to appreciate, you know, the wonders of creation in a way that
other people cannot and you're not doing it, so this is a
terrible sort of thing that you are depriving yourself religiously and therefore
you have this condemnation. No, not חייב מיתה, chayav misa, he just
said you shouldn't talk to this guy. So you have this condemnation.
Now that's because maybe you're, you know, your own religious well-being you're
not helping. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on, אמר רבי שמואל בר
נחמני אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rebbe Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rebbe Yochanan,
מנין שמצוה על אדם לחשב תקופות ומזלות, minayin shemitzvah al adam lachashev
tkufos umazalos, how do you know it's a מצוה mitzvah to do
this? And does that mean if you're able maybe you're supposed to
learn the math in order to do it? שנאמר, shene'emar, as the
verse says, ושמרתם ועשיתם כי היא חכמתכם ובינתכם לעיני העמים. ushmartem va'asitem
ki hi chochmaschem ubinaschem le'einei ha'amim. You should observe these מצוות mitzvos
because it is your wisdom in the eyes of the nations. איזו
חכמה ובינה שהיא לעיני העמים? eizu chochma ubinah shehi le'einei ha'amim? What
is a type of wisdom and understanding that even the nations will
understand and appreciate? הוי אומר זה חישוב תקופות ומזלות. hevei omer zeh
chishuv tkufos umazalos. It is figuring the constellations. Why is that something
that they will appreciate the wisdom? Because Rashi says, you'll say look,
in this day this is what's going to happen and the stars
will be here and the planets will be here, and then comes
that day and it happens. So you actually have direct evidence of
your intelligence and therefore it shows how wise the Jews are and
it shows our wisdom to the nations. Of course, interestingly, we're not
claiming it's based on anything in the תורה, Torah, we just know
how like we are, we're smart people, not that the תורה Torah
is חכמתכם ובינתכם, chochmaschem ubinaschem, that's quite fascinating. The other thing Rashi
of course says is talking about what they believed about this חישוב
תקופות ומזלות. chishuv tkufos umazalos. It's not just where the planets are,
but also the way they will affect things down on the earth.
So you know Rashi talks about like, you know, is Saturn in
ascendancy?
And those types of more astrological types of considerations. Also they very
much believed was a science, and רש''י Rashi says that's also what
you demonstrate that on this day these types of things are going
to
happen. Yes.
Well this would be evidence against the people who say that you
can learn all science from the Torah because it's not mentioned.
אדרבה, Adderaba, you could say the fact that it's connecting it to
the פסוק pasuk of כי חכמתכם ובינתכם Ki Chochmaschem u'binaschem is telling
you there's a way to get this out of the Torah. So
anyway, what I actually thought was interesting is when you have אמר
רבי יוחנן מנין שמצוה על אדם, Amar Rabbi Yochanan minayin she-mitzvah al
adam, there's a little ג gimmel which says that it's פוסקין paskin
in הלכה. halacha. So I was looking up, I was expecting to
find the רמב''ם Rambam because you know, the רמב''ם Rambam does have
just turn certain areas of science and intellectual pursuit into מצוות. mitzvos.
But here actually it's interesting, it's in the סמ''ג, Smag, it's not
in the רמב''ם. Rambam. But the רמב''ם Rambam does have the learning
of natural sciences as a מצוה. mitzvah. He has it as a
מצוה mitzvah of אהבת השם Ahavas Hashem that by which is very
much connects to what this גמרא Gemara is saying, right, את פועל
השם לא יביטו, es po'al Hashem lo yabbitu, that by appreciating the
wisdom of creation, you know, that leads to אהבת השם Ahavas Hashem
and also according to the רמב''ם Rambam leads to יראת השם. Yiras
Hashem. So the רמב''ם Rambam actually does have this as a מצוה,
mitzvah, although not necessarily with a particular emphasis on תקופות ומזלות. tkufos
u'mazalos. Yes.
So according to the רמב''ם, Rambam, if the first thing I read
in the morning before going to שול shul is Scientific American, I
should be required to say ברכת התורה? Birkas HaTorah?
Okay, so we're not discussing that right now. Moving on. הצד צבי,
Hatzad Tzvi, now somebody who catches a deer. So, תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabbanan.
הצד חלזון והפוצעו, Hatzad chilazon vehapotzo, now in the so again the
question is what was in the משכן, Mishkan, right? Because now in
the משכן Mishkan they did have to trap certain animals to skin
them because they had עורות אילים מאדמים ועורות תחשים orot eilim me'odamim
ve'orot techashim etc. So that could have been, but the גמרא Gemara
now applies them to the capturing of snails. So הצד חלזון Hatzad
chilazon if you capture the snails from which they derive
the blood to get the תכלת. techeiles. So if somebody captures snails
והפוצעו vehapotzo and you squeeze it out to get out the blood,
אינו חייב אלא אחת. eino chayav ela achas. You only transgress one
for צידה. tzeida. ורבי יהודה אומר חייב שתים. Ve-Rabbi Yehuda omer chayav
shtayim. You get two. שהיה רבי יהודה אומר פציעה בכלל דישה. She-haya
Rabbi Yehuda omer ptzi'ah bichlal disha. This squeezing out is like דישה.
disha. Remember דישה disha is threshing, it's like squeezing out an orange
to get out orange juice, getting something out of its container as
it were, its natural container. So here you're squeezing the blood out
of the snail, so it's דישה. disha. אמרו
לו אין פציעה בכלל דישה.
Amru lo
ein ptzi'ah bichlal disha.
It's not included. אמר רבא מאי טעמא דרבנן, Amar Rava mai ta'ama
d'Rabbanan, what's the reason of the Rabbis? קסברי אין דישה אלא בגידולי
קרקע. Kasavri ein disha ela b'gidulei karka. דישה Disha only applies by
things that grow from the ground and therefore does not apply to
snails. Okay, and you only do דישה disha on agricultural products. Now
the big question is how about milking cows? Because there's another גמרא
Gemara that says it's מפרק, mefarek, so some want to say, well,
according if we פוסקין paskin אין דישה אלא בגידולי קרקע, ein disha
ela b'gidulei karka, milking would only be דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Okay, others say
maybe milking is an
exception.
There are some interests, well before I say that I'll say, one
possible approach is that maybe animals, land animals are considered a broader
category of גידולי קרקע. gidulei karka. Snails are sea animals, but land
animals live off the ground, so earth, so maybe they're also included
in גידולי קרקע. gidulei karka. תוספות Tosafos suggests that but rejects it,
but that's a possibility. An interesting third possibility, which is going to
be shocking, is that according to some
ראשונים Rishonim and
פוסקים, Poskim, some of the limitations on the אבות avos do not
apply to the תולדות. toldos. So even if דישה disha is only
by גידולי קרקע, gidulei karka, if מפרק mefarek which is the
תולדה toldah is maybe that doesn't have the limit, which is of
course completely bizarre and ironic. And you also wonder, isn't this how
is this any different than like the milking and if it's a
limitation here, it should be a limitation there. But just a little
bit of a thing to remember that this limit of דישה disha
on גידולי קרקע gidulei karka has a very significant implication for the
issue about milking. It also comes up even if we're not farmers
about women expressing milk on שבת. Shabbos. So to what degree is
that a דאורייתא d'oreisa or דרבנן d'rabbanan concern. Now the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi,
תוספות Tosafos quotes the ירושלמי Yerushalmi that says no, that the question
is not whether you're חייב chayav because of דישה, disha, the question
is whether you're חייב chayav because of צידה. tzeida. This might not
be considered צד. tzad. Now the ירושלמי Yerushalmi doesn't say why and
תוספות Tosafos doesn't say why. It seems to me the reason might
be, now that we realize snails, I mean for a long time
they assumed that this חלזון chilazon was a type of a fish,
now we know that it's snails. If you assume snails, it's an
interesting question is that considered צידה. tzeida. You have to go and
scoop them up, but it's not like they're running away, right? So
to what degree do you call it trapping? It requires like extracting
them, finding and extracting, but would you really call that an act
of trapping? So that's the ירושלמי Yerushalmi raises that issue. So let's
take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues.
So it doesn't have צד tzad and דישה. disha. And the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi said
צד, tzad, we're talking about the בבלי. Bavli. Okay, yes.
What about a woman getting milk though, saving life on?
Yeah, yeah, I'm not פוסק, paskening, I'm just raising the issues that
get raised.
Okay, so okay, fine. וליחייב נמי משום נטילת נשמה. V'lechayeiv nami mishum
netilat neshama. How about killing it, right? That's like we're going to
say שחטינג shechting an animal and we're going to say שחטינג shechting
is part of נטילת נשמה, netilat neshama, taking a life. So why
isn't that also a חיוב? chiyuv? אמר רבי יוחנן שפצאו מת. Amar
Rabbi Yochanan shepetza'o meit. Oh, it was already dead before you squeezed
it. Okay.
But it was alive. And it didn't, it didn't die in anyway.
Well, so that's a question. Is the fact that you extract them
from the ocean also נטילת נשמה? netilat neshama? So תוספות Tosafot discusses
that a little bit. About does it happen immediate? Does it contribute
to it? But he's killing them, right?
Otherwise he'd be, it'd be another one.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. רבא אמר אפילו תימא שפצאו חי, Rava amar afilu
teima shepetza'o chai, even if you're doing it while it's alive, מתעסק
הוא אצל נטילת נשמה. mit'asek hu eitzel netilat neshama. It's only incidental
that it's dying. Now תוספות Tosafot says the word here about מתעסק
mit'asek is not precise, but what it means is you're not intending
to do it, so therefore it's called what? דבר שאינו מתכוין. davar
she'eino mitkavein. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask about that.
One minute. ואביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו, V'Abaye v'Rava d'amri tarveihu, Abaye and
Rava both say מודה רבי שמעון בפסיק רישא ולא ימות. modeh Rabbi
Shimon b'psik reisha v'lo yamut. Rabbi Shimon agrees that if you, you
can't cut off the head of something and say I'm not intending
for it to die. You can't squeeze a snail till its last
drop of blood and say I'm not intending for it to die.
So it might be אינו מתכוין, eino mitkavein, but it's a פסיק
רישא, psik reisha, and therefore you should still be חייב chayav for
that,
okay? So the גמרא Gemara says no, שאני הכא, shani hacha, here
it's different. דכמה דאית ביה נשמה טפי ניחא ליה. d'kama d'it beih
neshama t'fei nicha leih. As long as it remains alive, you prefer
it alive. כי היכי דליציל צבעיה, ki heichi d'litzil tziv'eih, in order
that the color should be clear. Apparently if you, the blood that's
coming out while it's alive is a better blood to use than
if it comes out when it's dead, so you're trying to keep
it alive as long as possible. So what would be called that?
A פסיק רישא דלא ניחא ליה psik reisha d'lo nicha leih that
you don't want the end result and therefore even if it necessarily
happens, you're not going to be חייב chayav for that type of
a case. Now רש״י Rashi interestingly said, says, says, okay, but if
you are, if you are like, you know, don't care about whether
it dies or not. Not you specifically don't want it, but if
you're indifferent to whether it dies, you would be חייב. chayav. תוספות
Tosafot like goes crazy. תוספות Tosafot says what do you mean? And
he proves from other גמרות Gemoras that even a פסיק רישא דלא
איכפת ליה, psik reisha d'lo ichpat leih, right, there are three possible
things. You specifically don't want the end result, which is לא ניחא.
lo nicha. You're indifferent, לא איכפת. lo ichpat. And you דווקא dafka
do want the end result, which I guess would be איכפת ליה.
ichpat leih. Okay, so רש״י Rashi says if it's לא ניחא ליה
lo nicha leih you're exempt, but if it's just לא איכפת ליה,
lo ichpat leih, at least this רש״י, Rashi, other רש״י Rashi says
otherwise, you would be חייב. chayav. תוספות Tosafot says absolutely no, even
לא איכפת ליה lo ichpat leih you're exempt and as a general
rule הלכה, halacha, there is no difference between לא ניחא lo nicha
and לא איכפת. lo ichpat. Once you are indifferent to the result,
it doesn't make it מותר, mutar, but at least you are not
חייב, chayav, okay? And that is what the גמרא Gemara is saying
here. So now the גמרא Gemara continues,
והשוחטו. v'hashochto. So we're moving from trapping the deer, which again is
also discussed later, to שחטינג shechting the deer. So the גמרא Gemara
says, שוחט משום מאי חייב. shochet mishum mai chayav. What do you
חייב chayav for if you שחט shecht an animal? Now the גמרא
Gemara says, what do you mean? It just said השוחטו. hashochto. Well,
no, but that doesn't matter, that's a previous סוגיא. sugya. So תוספות
Tosafot says we're not asking on our משנה. Mishnah. Clearly our משנה
Mishnah sees it as one of the categories called שחיטה. shechitah. But
we're saying, you know, we're trying to get to the heart of
if you שחט shecht a normal animal, what is conceptually that category,
you know? So רבא אמר משום צובע, Rava amar mishum tzovei'a, you
are coloring. The blood colors the skin of the neck of the
animal you just שחט. shecht. ושמואל אמר משום נטילת נשמה. v'Shmuel amar
mishum netilat neshama. What are you talking about? It's cause you took
the life, which is what the category of שחיטה shechitah is about.
So the גמרא Gemara says, משום צובע אין משום נטילת נשמה לא?
mishum tzovei'a in mishum netilat neshama lo? We're now on ע״ה ע״ב.
ayin hei amud beit. According to רבא, Rava, according to רבא, Rava,
צובע tzovei'a yes, משום נטילת נשמה mishum netilat neshama no? Not killing?
So of course that's the main category. אימא אף משום צובע. Eima
af mishum tzovei'a. No, what רבא Rava meant to say is you
get a double חיוב. chiyuv. One you took the life and two
you colored the skin.
And you want the skin colored?
Well, right. So now,
אמר רבא מילתא דאמרי אימא בה מילתא דלא ליתו דרא בתראי וליחכו
עלי. Amar Rava milta d'amri eima bah milta d'lo leitu dara batra'ei
v'lichachu alai. I have to say something to explain it so later
generations come and don't mock me. Like, what type of crazy thing
he said, צובע? tzovei'a? Who cares if the skin is colored? So
let me explain myself. במאי ניחא ליה? B'mai nicha leih? Why do
you care? Why do you want this thing? That we should say
that, you know, rather than just saying again like we said before,
okay, פסיק רישא לא ניחא ליה psik reisha lo nicha leih etc.
Why do you want this that we could say that that's either
פסיק רישא דניחא ליה psik reisha d'nicha leih or it's ממש mamash
your כוונה? kavanah? So במאי ניחא ליה, ניחא ליה דליטנף בית השחיטה
דמא. B'mai nicha leih, nicha leih d'litnef beit hash'chita dama. You want
for the place where you שחט shecht to actually be stained with
blood and to be colored with blood. Why? Not just on the
surface but presumably to get in and color it. כי היכי דליחזי
אינשי וליתו וליזבנו מיניה. ki heichi d'lichazei inshi v'leitu v'lizbnu mineih. It
looks nice and red and it looks like, you know, fresh meat.
So if you have that sort of bloodstained neck, people know that
it was recently שחטed, shecht and therefore they will come and buy
it. So you actually do want the blood to stain the neck
and that is helpful for you, and therefore you also have that
חיוב. chiyuv. Yes?
For some animals you have to cover the blood. Yes, but that
would involve moving מוקצה. muktzah.
So that's the first משנה Mishnah in ביצה. Beitzah. When you are
שחטינג shechting on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Well, so that would be,
it's a difference between שבת Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom Tov. on
יום טוב Yom Tov about how do you do the covering of
the blood. Okay, but we're talking here that you're not allowed to
do it, and we're talking about what you're חייב chayav for. Okay,
so there we dealt with שחיטה shechita and נטילת נשמה. netilas neshama.
Now I should say that generally making a wound, as we'll see,
is called a type of נטילת נשמה, netilas neshama, and תוספות Tosafos
has a question, what is the נטילת נשמה netilas neshama of making
the wound? So he says, well, you could say maybe it's cause
you injure somebody and injury is like on the, you know, as
a stage towards נטילת נשמה, netilas neshama, but he rejects that because
the
גמרא—whatever—then Gemara you would never have that it wouldn't be—there are many
cases where you wouldn't want that result and we still call it
חייב. chayav. So תוספות Tosafos says רבנו תם's Rabbeinu Tam famous position
that all these cases that you're חייב chayav are cases where blood
comes out. I mean, if you—actually that you don't actually kill, like
you could kill something with no blood coming out, like you could
kill, I don't know, what are some of those bugs—well, you could
strangle somebody—let's not worry about talking about people, that's whatever—anyway, but let's
say you could kill a lizard or something, right? There's no blood.
Okay, that would be נטילת נשמה. netilas neshama. But when blood comes
out, if you wound somebody even, then that's also חייב chayav and
רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam says כי הדם הוא הנפש, ki hadam hu
hanefesh, that the blood represents the soul and therefore taking blood is
like taking soul and that puts it in the נטילת נשמה. netilas
neshama. So that's why we have basically two categories. One is killing
an animal, let's say, and the other is taking of blood, which
is נטילת נשמה. netilas neshama. So תוספות Tosafos then asks—I should just
say—so when you're squeezing the חילזון, chilazon, you're taking out the blood.
Why aren't you חייב chayav there also for נטילת נשמה netilas neshama
for like wounding and so on? He gives a certain answer, but
I just wanted to frame the issue of what's included in this—or
might be included in this—נטילת נשמה. netilas neshama. Let's go on. Let's
see if we can make it to the משנה. mishna. והמולחו והמעבדו,
vehamolcho veha'amevdo, if you salt the leather and you work it. So
the גמרא Gemara says היינו מולח היינו מעבד, hainu moleach hainu me'aved,
salting is working it. It's part of the process. First you would
salt it, then you would walk on it, but anyway, it's part
of the process. Why are we making it a different category? So
רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש—אמרו תרווייהו, they both say—אפיק חד מינייהו, afik chad
mineihu, fine, take one of those out, ועייל שרטוט, ve'ayyel sirtut, and
put in something that was missing. Part of the process of making
the leather, of making the cloth or whatever, is making lines in
it, like lines, cut along this line, right? If you're working on
something in leather, you know, you make a line with a ruler
and then you take your knife and you cut along the line.
So that type of making a line, שרטוט, sirtut, is also—is also
חייב. chayav. Again, what exactly is the context of this—lines just for
cutting, lines to signify anything? Anyway, but this is a new מלאכה
melacha of שרטוט. sirtut. Yeah, they change the משנה. mishna. I don't
know what to tell you. Again, it shows that there's a certain,
you know, flexibility in these thirty-nine categories, they're still sort of crystallizing.
And they agreed?
And they agreed.
What happens
to getting to thirty-nine?
Well, to get to thirty-nine, we took out one of those two
and we had to put in another one.
אמר רבה בר
רב הונא,
Amar
Rabba bar
Rav Huna, האי מאן דמלח ביסרא, hai man demalach bisra, so now
we're moving on. So now we've—but the interesting thing is, if you
took one out, presumably you would take out מולח, moleach, salting, and
leave it as מעבד. me'aved. Now, if your category is מעבד me'aved
and not salting, then you would think that for something to be
a תולדה, tolada, it has to be similar to a process—like related
to some type of thing like the process of making leather. But
if you focus on מולח moleach by itself, salting by itself, then
you could discuss salting other objects. It has nothing to do with,
like, transforming them or so on. So let's take a look, cause
now the גמרא Gemara seems to phone—hone in on מולח moleach as
its own category. האי מאן דמלח ביסרא, Hai man demalach bisra, if
you salt meat, which they would do to preserve it, חייב משום
מעבד, chayav mishum me'aved, he's חייב chayav for מעבד. me'aved. Okay, so
that is a type of—it's מולח, moleach, but they're calling, again, the
category not מולח, moleach, they're calling the category מעבד. me'aved. So רבא
אמר, Rava amar, אין עיבוד באוכלין. ein ibud be'ochlin. No, I'm sorry.
You don't have עיבוד ibud by foods. עיבוד ibud you do by
materials that you're trying to somehow transform. So if you put salt
on, I don't know, some wood to treat it, maybe that would
be a type of a מעבד. me'aved. But food is food, and
therefore it's not considered—עיבוד ibud is fundamentally excluded. So it's interesting, on
the one hand we have some things that are only said by
גידולי קרקע. gidulei karka. We have other types of categories that basically
are explicitly excluded from them are foods. אין עיבוד באוכלין. ein ibud
be'ochlin. Another example would be צביעה באוכלין, tvia be'ochlin, right, adding food
coloring and so on. So here it is explicitly excluding, this is
about objects, not about foods. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi,
ואפילו רבה בר רב הונא לא אמר, ve'afilu Rabba bar Rav Huna
lo amar, even רבה בר רב הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna who
said you can have עיבוד ibud by food, he didn't say it
אלא דקבעי ליה לאורחא, ela deka'ba'i lei le'orcha, that you are really
salting it because you're going to go on a, you know, three-month
journey. You're basically making like beef jerky or something. You're, you know,
you're salting it to preserve it for a very long time. And
then you've really like transformed it and maybe that's sort of like
the idea of the leather, you completely extract the moisture, you make
it hard, you transform. So that's what, if that's the case he's
talking
about. אבל לביתא, Aval leveisa, if you're salting it because you're going
to use it in your house a few days later, לא מצוי
איניש דמשוי מיכלי עץ, lo matzi inish demashvei michlei etz, people don't
make their food into wood. So therefore, that it would not be—I
agree, it has to be really transformative. that it would not be
בר מיניה, bar minei, I agree, it has to be really transformative
and not a normal type of home-based salting. But the other פירוש
peireish says I don't care how transformative it is, fundamentally food is
excluded from this category. Okay, so that is מליח moleiach plus the
new category of שרטוט. sirtut. Now I'll just show you in the
in this cute little book here.
Yes, can salting be considered a form of cooking?
So that's interesting like salting like herring or something like that preparing.
Yeah, so no, cooking is only with heat. So there is a
question though about, you know, salting in other contexts. But yeah, let
me just show you here. He totally skipped by the way our
whole lovely weaving thing. There's going to be another פרק perek devoted
to it. But here anyway, okay, he, the,
here I just wanted to show you what he includes in
this. Okay, with the מעבד. me'abeid. Okay, he's got hammering leather to
soften it. Yeah, too bad I was about to do that on
שבת. Shabbos. Brushing Buccia shoes with a special cream to soften the
leather. So both of those are obvious applications about working the leather,
not signing with the, not shining, but something that softens, that just
polishes. Okay, and now he's got a דרבנן d'rabanan here. Preparing a
large amount of very salty water if it appears it will be
used for salting. That's a special case. But here, more important in
going on Charlie's issues, pickling vegetables. Really using salt to transform food.
Okay, because אין עיבוד באוכלין, ein ibud be'ochlin, okay, but so even
though it's, and it's not בישול, bishul, but at least there's some
דרבנן d'rabanan of really using salt to, right, to transform. And then
he's got here, right, משרטט, mesarteit, the one that they just added,
right, and let me just see what examples he gives for that.
Yeah, so he has examples like,
again, things that are not just סתם stam lines but for a
particular purpose. So,
what is it?
Like on a
roll of paper, right?
Outlining for cutting, marking objects for folding,
etching lines for writing. So it's not just making lines, but it's
making lines that are then going to be used to cut, to
write on, and so on. Okay. Alright, so somehow are transforming this
object, you know, because it gets it to the next stage of
usability. Alright, let's keep on, let's keep on going.
הממחקו והמחתכו. hamemacheiko vehamachateicho. If you sort of ממחק, memacheik, like scrape
the leather, but that becomes a new problem of not scraping, but
of smoothing. We've already seen some applications to that. Actually, going back
to Michael's point there about like shaving or whatever. That's exactly what
this is. This is smoothing in the process of scraping stuff off.
והמחתכו, vehamachateicho, and then cutting the leather and we mentioned that מחתך
machateich is to a precise size or to a size that you
care about, you know, it's not like a random cut. So אמר
רב אמי בר חנינא: amar Rav Ami bar Chanina:
השך בין העמודים בשבת חייב מיתה.
hashach bein
ha'amudim beShabbos chayav misa. If you rub against the pillars that they
had in like a portico on שבת, Shabbos, you're חייב מיתה. chayav
misa. Why? משום ממחק. mishum memacheik. For smoothing. So what are you
smoothing? So רש״י Rashi says you're if you're sort of, you know,
was walking, you know, smoothing the ground, the floor below to make
it nice and smooth, presumably your intention is doing that. תוספות Tosafos
says that doesn't make sense because he doesn't say why, but presumably
if that were a problem it would be a בונה boneh problem,
it wouldn't be a ממחק memacheik problem. I mean, but anyway, תוספות
Tosafos does not like that explanation. He doesn't say why. He says
that it means that you're actually rubbing up leather against the pillars
and you actually are it's a direct application of smoothing the leather.
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא... amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba... I don't
know. ג' דברים סח לי רב אסי משמיה דרבי יהושע או רב
אסי משמיה דרבי יהושע בן לוי. gimel devarim sach li Rav Asi
mishmeih deRabbi Yehoshua o Rav Asi mishmeih deRabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. Three
things רב אסי Rav Asi whispered to me in the name of
רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. Number one: המגרר ראשי
קלונוסו בשבת חייב משום מחתך. hamegarer roshei klonoso beShabbat chayav mishum machateich.
If you basically take like a pole and you you know, you
make a point you you
you know, you whittle it on שבת, Shabbos, that's מחתך. machateich. It's
cutting. Because it's a cutting and you're trying to create something very
specific like you're trying to get it to a point, okay, so
that's again מחתך. machateich. Not just סתם stam you're cutting something away,
you're actually cutting it in a precise way, you're making a point.
That's מחתך. machateich. But it's not ממחק, memacheik, it's not smoothing, even
though presumably you smooth along the way. What this seems to be
saying is, you know, we'll give it the more specific category before
we give it the more broad category. הממרח רטיה בשבת, hamemareiach ritya
beShabbat,
and this is extremely important for salves and the toothpaste question, somebody
smooths on some type of a רטיה ritya on שבת Shabbos like
some type of a mixed thing that goes on a wound, חייב
משום ממחק. chayav mishum memacheik. That is smoothing. So this is something
you would have said shouldn't be included because you don't necessarily want
smooth, you just want to apply it. And nevertheless, right, and you're
not fixing the thing that it's being smoothed on, and nevertheless the
גמרא Gemara says it's חייב משום ממחק. chayav mishum memacheik. And that
gets to all the issues about dabbing on stuff rather than smoothing
it on. We'll talk about that later? A little bit maybe. והמסתת
את האבן בשבת חייב משום מכה בפטיש. vehamasatet es ha'even beShabbat chayav
mishum makeh befatish. It's מכה בפטיש. makeh befatish. Now why? Why isn't
it ממחק? memacheik? This would seem to be a classic
smoothing... is like you make like you know something like they have
like an edge on the stone, like a little, like you know,
indentation to make a square like indented, you know, around the edges
and therefore, yeah, that is the last, that is the last act
that is done and therefore it is considered מכה בפטיש. makeh b'pattish.
אמר רבי שמעון בן קיסמא אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי הצייר ציורא
בכלי, Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Kisma amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi hatziyar
tziyura b'chli, if you make some final decoration in a vessel
והמנפח בכלי זכוכית v'hamnafeiach b'chli zchuchit or if you blow into a
glass vessel to again do some final little adjustment, חייב משום מכה
בפטיש. chayav mishum makeh b'pattish. Again, מכה בפטיש makeh b'pattish is this
generic thing which is you do the last little act that makes
it now finished. And that's מכה בפטיש. makeh b'pattish. Okay. There's huge
literature on this because this could be all inclusive. All right? So
I'm not going to now try to discuss the exact different nuanced
parameters, but the basic idea is that last little act that makes
it finished. אמר רבי יהודה האי מאן דשקיל אקופי מגלימי חייב משום
מכה בפטיש. Amar Rabbi Yehuda hai man d'shakal akufei miglmei chayav mishum
makeh b'pattish. If you take a thread out of a garment, right
sometimes a garment is done and it still has like some threads
left and you remove that last thread, that's also מכה בפטיש. makeh
b'pattish. That last hanging thread. Even one? Even one? והני מילי דקפיד
עלייהו, V'hani mili d'kapeid alayhu, that's only if you care about it.
If it's trivial, it's interesting, then even though it is finishing it,
it doesn't matter now. That is presumably also that it never was
finished. Let's say you buy your jacket and the pockets are sewn
up. Okay. Now you could talk about מתיר, matir, okay undoing a
whatever, not מתיר, matir, קורע koreia or something, it's not קורע koreia
but תפור, tfor, but is it מכה בפטיש? makeh b'pattish? Probably not
because it was already finished and then they sewed it up. מכה
בפטיש makeh b'pattish is the last thing in the stage of finishing
it. Okay, let's just give me two more minutes we'll read to
the משנה. mishnah.
והכותב שתי אותיות,
V'hakoteiv shtei otiyot, two letters. תנו רבנן: Tano Rabbanan: כתב אות אחת
גדולה ויש במקומה לכתוב שתים פטור. Katav ot achat gdola v'yeish b'komah
lichtov shtayim patur. If
you write a huge letter and you could have fit two letters
in that space that took you to write one letter, doesn't matter,
you're exempt, you only wrote one letter. But, מחק אות גדולה ויש
במקומה לכתוב שתים, machak ot gdola v'yeish b'komah lichtov shtayim, if you
erased a big letter
and you left over a cloth now the erased space has space
to write two letters, חייב, chayav, you are liable. Because even if
it was an ink blot you'd be חייב. chayav. Well that's not
necessarily true, it might have to be you erase something significant. But
anyway, but it's erasing על מנת לכתוב, al m'nat lichtov, and therefore
it's not whether there were two letters you erased, but is there
a space to write two letters. אמר רבי מנחם ברבי יוסי זה
חומר במוחק מבכותב. Amar Rabbi Menachem b'Rabbi Yosi zeh chomer b'mochek mib'koteiv.
There's
this is an example where erasing is is more stringent than actual
writing. Okay, last group: הבונה והסותר והמכבה והמבעיר והמכה בפטיש. Haboneh v'hasoteir
v'hamchabeh v'hamaveir v'hamakeh b'pattish.
All things related to building, don't worry we'll get other פרקים prokim
about them. Building, destroying, putting out a fire, making a fire, and
מכה בפטיש. makeh b'pattish. רבה ורב זירא דאמרי תרווייהו, Rabba v'Rav Zeira
d'amri duvayhu, we skipped the whole list go to the end: כל
מידי דאית ביה גמר מלאכה חייב משום מכה בפטיש. Kol midi d'it
bei gmar melacha chayav mishum makeh b'pattish. Anything that is the last
act of making something is מכה בפטיש, makeh b'pattish, giving a nice
round up to the things we mentioned before about the carving in
the stone and the drawing of the vessel, anything that basically is
that last act is מכה בפטיש. makeh b'pattish. The very end of
the משנה: mishnah: אלו אבות מלאכות. Eilu avot melachot. We also skipped
the carrying, we've done a lot of carrying don't worry we're about
to do more. Anyway these are the אבות מלאכות. avot melachot. אלו,
Eilu, these, לאפוקי מדרבי אליעזר, l'apukei mid'Rabbi Eliezer, to exclude the position
of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer דמחייב על תולדה במקום אב. d'mechayev al
tolada b'makom av. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that if you do
an אב av and its תולדה, tolada, you would actually bring two
חטאות. chatatot. If you do the same אב av multiple times it's
only one, but an אב av and its תולדה. tolada. Until now
we've been saying you can only get thirty-nine. He actually says the
sky's the limit, you know, because every תולדה tolada is distinct from
the אב. av. So אלו, eilu, no, only these, there's only going
to be thirty-nine. חסר אחת. Chasar achat. Then why do we again
repeat the number? We said in the beginning and the end. לאפוקי
מדרבי יהודה, L'apukei mid'Rabbi Yehuda, to exclude רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא
רבי יהודה מוסיף את השובט ואת המדקדק. D'tanya Rabbi Yehuda mosif et
hashoveit v'et hamaddek. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda adds two. He's got forty-one.
Not everybody holds of thirty-nine. What does he add? שובט Shoveit which
is type of a way of
banging the strings into the loom and מדקדק maddek is a way
of also like banging it as you're weaving to smooth out the
the threads that are being woven. We'll talk about it later when
we get into detail. So אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to
him: שובט הרי הוא בכלל מיסך. Shoveit harei hu bichlal meiseich. No,
שובט shoveit is included in setting up the loom because this is
also a way of, you know, part of the process of setting
up the loom. ומדקדק, V'maddek, banging the strings smooth, הרי הוא בכלל
אורג. harei hu bichlal oreig. That's part of the process of weaving,
so these are not separate categories, and we will continue with this
tomorrow.